<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caueat for the Christians agaynst the arch-papist</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117729</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852939</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852939</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18294</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18685)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18294)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 20:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caueat for the Christians agaynst the arch-papist</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Foster lane by [N. Hill for] Iohn Wally,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher's name from colophon; actual printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Title page border (McKerrow and Ferguson 33) has initials "J W" in the slot in the sill.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18294:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A CAVEAT for the Chriſtians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>papiſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ioh, iii.</bibl>
               <p>This is the condemnation, that lyght is come into the worlde, and men loued dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes more then lyghte, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe their dedes wer euyl.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. xvi.</bibl>
               <p>Take hede and beware of the leuen of the Phariſes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>1548</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>illustrated border</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18294:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O Englyſhe men, that runne ſo</l>
               <l>well, let no man you forſpeake.</l>
               <l>For God (no doubt) ſhall iudge</l>
               <l>the man, that you to ſtop ſhal ſeke.</l>
               <l>Temper your ſelfes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> than runne</l>
               <l>the race, that ye may wyn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown.</l>
               <l>And not the crown y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> periſſheth,</l>
               <l>but that ſhall neuer downe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18294:2"/>
            <head>¶ An admonition for all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to beware of the Phariſaicall le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, of the Archepapiſt,<note place="margin">Hereis not half his worthy ſtyle.</note> the gloriouſe Hipocrite the ſubtile Sopheſter, and the fraudulent cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trefeyctour of Gods holy worde: Where the abſurditee of his late abuſed termes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratinge himſelfe in remembraunce of himſelfe is merely well refelled, confuted and audyded: And at the laſt the ſelfe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des (thorowe the conference of ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues) reſtored to theſe olde ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and trewe meanynge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vrely good Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I can do no leſſe of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toad moniſhe you of a certayne notable Papiſt who (accordyng to hys accuſtomed maner) dyd priue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truſte in to a greate lump of dowe euen a lytle leuen but truely no leſſe than leuened the whole doughe. The confection and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the leuen was after thys
<pb facs="tcp:18294:3"/>ſorte, Conſecrating himſelf in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of him ſelf. Nowe you maye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the leuen is a very lytle pece in quantitee but yet veray greate in qualitte (I meane of ſowernes. For it was digged vp of the ſlimy pyttes of mannes doctrine, and ſeaſoned not wyth the water of life but with very poddel water which hath bene ſo long kepte in the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peg fylthye ceſternes that nowe it ſtynketh agayne, not in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes noſeg (who haue euer be brought vp with it, and haue ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned euen their mooſte delycate wafrons therwith) but in the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſenſe that lyue on the newe water of the welſprynge that ſo ſwetely ſauoureth of Chriſt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (I ſave) let vs with all ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour go about to auoyde thys vn ſauerye leauen, for it is nothynge worth but to be eiecte and caſt out and troden downe of men vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote.
<pb facs="tcp:18294:3"/>For it hathe in it no whit of the ſalt of trew wyſedome, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſmellyng of carnall wit, worldely inuention, and deuely ſhe imaginacion. Pourge therfore the olde leuen, that ye maye be newe dowe, as ye are ſwete breade. But I praye you where ſhall a manne fynde ſuche wordes or any equiua lent to thoſe leuenouſe woordes of his, among all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of Chriſt ſpoken at his laſt ſupper: And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely I would neuer haue thought that a man beyng no leſſe polityke than learned woulde ſo pertly and ſo portely, ſo openly and ſo opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vtter his Phranſye and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe either his hereſie or ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie after ſuche ſort as he dyd, and that before the chiefe in earthe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes churche, and before the eyes &amp; wyſedome of al the wholeroialme. But yet I praye you holde the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cxcuſed for he nedes muſte ſo do,
<pb facs="tcp:18294:4"/>els his perled mytre ſhulde haue maxed lyke a Chriſtenmans cap: his pontifical maieſtie ſhuld haue bene more miniſterlyke, his holye crochear muſt haue be more ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoke lyke. Els the God of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare ſhulde be remetamorphoſed, vniuggled, and vnconiured again into a wafron cake: The Iewyſhe ſtony alter ſhulde haue no longer ſtande in ſtede. The leuiticall dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyſed veſtimentes with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the Hopyſh churches ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, ſhulde cleane haue vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed away, and the whole flocke of popyſhe ſecre (of whom he was the chiefe and ſureſt leanynge poſt) ſhulde haue fall down into a dead<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſwone: and all Eardiners garde ſhulde neuer be regarded. But yet I ſay I woulde neuer haue expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuche newe founde termes to haue guſhed out at his mouth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng a man no leſſe ware, than wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:18294:4"/>no leſſe wyly, than circomſpecte, no leſſe circomſpecte than worldly wyſe: Sauinge onelye the ſacred Scripture muſte be true, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des muſte be fulfylled which ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>I will deſtroye the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the wyſe / and wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſt a way the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the prudent.<note place="margin">Eſa. xxix.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therfore let vs geue thankes with oure Lorde Ieſu vnto God the father, that he hath hyd his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine iniſteries from the wyſe and ſheweth them vnto babes: verelye we ſe nowe that it ſo pleaſeth hys mooſt druine maieſtee. But to you maſter Craftye (and pleaſeth your conſecration) me thynketh ye were a lytle to folyſhe hardy to bragge out your ſelf before ſo couragious a Lyon who could daſihe, quayle,
<pb facs="tcp:18294:5"/>&amp; hwiſht al your bragginges with the leſt rorynge of his mouth.<note place="margin">Prou. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> Me thynketh, ye toke a lytle to muche payne, to go about to caſt duſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuche mens eyes as there were: for they cold clearely forſe whether tended your duſty endeuour wyth out any forayn ſpectacles.</p>
            <p>O ſyg (I am ſorye for youre chaunce) ye were a lytle ouer ſene that ye woulde playe the Sophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſo kyndly, before ſo many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Logicians (as there were) who colde eſpie out your ſolemne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſopheſmes, and entryp you at their wyll and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But you knewe well ynough that ye ſhoulde not be diſputed nor reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wyth all, nor yet interrupted for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> while, and that by lyke made you ſo bolde to laſhe out what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer came vpon your tonges ende. But ſyra ſhall I be ſorye or you and the Papiſtes that ye ſpente ſo
<pb facs="tcp:18294:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>vaynely your Rhetorical colours? for there were in that Auditorye to greate a nombre that coulde eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye thorowe (for all youre freſhe colours and darke ſhadowynges) the rotten poſtes of the Romyſhe churche.</p>
            <p>But I promyſe you mayſter Sopheſter and ye hadde beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the ſaine goodly ambiguouſe ſermon of yours, in anye place elles in Englande (bothe the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities excepted) you ſhoulde haue lefte youre audyence in a greate doubte whether ye were an Archepapiſte or a microchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and whether ye leſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured mannes lawe or Goddes lawe.</p>
            <p>But in deade ye ſemed than, rather to kepe youre ſelfe wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the preſcripte boundes of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes lawe, than to leane to the ſure poſtes of Goddes lawe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18294:6"/>
            <p>Yea it was wyttyly done of you to kepe you ſtyl with in the reache of youre cauell, for thence you mought ſafely ſnarre and ſnatche at whom you woulde, if they dyd myſlyke your lordſhyppe: But I truſt you wyll ſaue one, yf mans pollecie can preuayle. But alas I am ſorye that deade mens boues (I do not meane. Barnes moare than others) are nowe ſene in your whyted ſepulchre: Yet I praye God (and his pleaſer be not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye) to auerte the vengeange of Saynetes prayers from you,<note place="margin">Apoea. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and to directe yet your harte to cleaue to the immaculate lawe of the Lorde, &amp; receyue the head cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone into your buyldynge. I praye God euen hartely to make you a new Chriſtian brother, of an old papiſtical Saul: I pray God that we maye haue iuſt occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to prayſe God of youre godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb facs="tcp:18294:6"/>And I pray God that ye haue not the power to play the .ii. pyked ſtaffe no more. For ye haue dalyed to long, ye haue diſſimuled to lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ye haue haulted on both ſydes to long: I pray God that you maye yet remembre the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men prouerbe that affirmeth euer to be better than neuer: yet may you be Paul, yf Chriſt wyll. And I praye you to be no more offended with thys my wrytyng than ye woulde haue me to be offended with youre ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: I forgiue you on my parte and I pray God forgeue you alſo: &amp; I pray you to do lykewyſe vnto me. For ſurely if ye be ſo wiſe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ye are eſtemed, ye woll rather couet to loke in a trew glaſſe, than in a flatteryng myrrour: But tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row your good pacience I muſte go about to pourge out that ſame lytle leauen that you hyd of late purpoſely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dowghy lumpe of
<pb facs="tcp:18294:7"/>your pharaſaicall ſermon. Why do not you yourſelfe knowe (but euery Chriſtian knoweth) that it is a ſower leuenouſe doctrine to alter the inſtitution fo the Lordes ſupper? And you knewe wel y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that all papiſtes and al the vnlearned people take this worde (conſecratinge) for tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, changing, or alteryng of the ſacramental bread and wyne into the very natural bodye of Chriſte (and as they call it) fleſhe bloude and bone: But I praye you was this well done of you? or where fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde (Conſecrating) of yours. But I am ſure ye wyll ſay that it counteruaileth benedixit whiche ſignifieth alſo in Englyſh (he bleſſed.) Wel I wyl graunt al that: but why than dyd you wreſt the bleſſynge into conſecration? Mary bicauſe it was a more glad ſome euangeli for your diſciples &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18294:7"/>a more to the ſome ſwillig for your hoggy ſhe Maſſers: but (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> triumph was but ſhort and the banket but a dreame. But paraduenture you wyl relent ſom what, and yelde ſo far (by cauſe ye can donone other) as to forgo this worde Conſecratynge, ſo that ye maye haue bleſſynge for it: Than ye wil procede and ſay that (he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hymſelfe) whiche (after youre mynde) is all one in effecte, as the Euangeliſt, had ſaid he conſecrated hymſelfe: why than be it ſo, for a whyle yet. But than from whence conueyed you in, that worde (him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) for there is no ſuche woorde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> texte: but tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil you ſtraight way ſay there is panis breade in the texte: That do I graunte alſo neue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rtheleſſe you ſpell to wel, and put to gether to faſt, if that ye wyl ſaye (he bleſſed the bread). I praye you of whence haue you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woorde
<pb facs="tcp:18294:8"/>(he bleſſed) Mary of benedixit but I pray you farther (by cauſe ye be learned in the tongues) tel me yet of whence had you that benedixit? you wyll ſay of <hi>eulogeſe</hi> the Greke worde whiche betokeneth in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloſhe he bleſſed, he prayſed, or he ſpake wel of. Wel in ſo much, that you tolde me what anſwered to benedixit in the Greke texte: I wyl lykewyſe tell you what anſwereth to it in the Hebrue. For I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, ye wil not denye but Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew wrote his Goſpell in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe: And wryteth <hi>ueieuarech</hi> for et benedirit and he bleſſed. How be it the Hebrue verbe <hi>barech</hi> betoke neth as wel and as indifferentlye <hi>(gratias egit)</hi> he, gaue thankes, as he bleſſed: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place may ſuffre to be ſo vnderſtande: And I praye you what place els in the whole ſcripture may better ſuffer yea or rather dothe require <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:18294:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>barech,</hi> to ſignifie to geue thankes more than this ſame place dothe I praye you was not euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Ieſus Chriſt before this tyme of his laſte ſupper, accuſtomed to geue thankes vnto his heauenly father at receyuyng of his bodely ſuſtenaunce or not? you woll par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture ſay nay: No, but than on what ſhall we grounde oure godly cuſtome of ſaying Grace or geuyng thankes vnto God, at meate tyme? It ſemeth to me that that laudable and godly ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye (as an imitacion of Chriſtes owne maner) came vp, emong the Chriſtians euen from his tyme. For the Euangeliſt Matthew in the .rxvi. cap, ſayeth <hi>Wcheſhamer weth-tehillah,</hi> that is: whan they had ſayde prayſe, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſaid grace, or whan they had geuen tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes: erge, there were more than Chriſte hymſelfe: And who ſhoulde, they
<pb facs="tcp:18294:9"/>be but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles whiche (as it be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth a diſciple) folowed their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters trade, &amp; ſo ſucceſſiuely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians accuſtomed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner vntyll this day. Yee but tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil you ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ther be .ii. kynd of Graces, one ſayde after meate named Gratias actioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thankes geuyng: and an other ſayd before meate called <hi>Conſecratio menſe</hi> the conſecration of the table, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng or halwyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meat. Now by all halowes it paſſeth my brai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to auoide thys blyſſynge and halowyng of yours, onles I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe out on the Angell of heauen who (and you will accepte it) ſhall anſwer you with the ſame wordes as he ſpake to Peter wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was of your opinion, his wordes were theſe: what God hath clenſed call not thou comun or vncleane. To the which Sainct Paule ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth on this wyſe:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18294:9"/>
            <p>All the treatures of God are good:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Tim. iiii</note>
            </p>
            <p>Than yf all maner of fourfoted beaſtes of the earth, and vermen,<note place="margin">Actuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .x.</note> and wormes, and foules of the ayer be cleane: And yf all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God be good, what neade thei than ſo muche of our bleſſing and halowyng? but we oughte in very dede to render moſt hygheſt thankes vnto God for his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſe lyberalitee of his creatures whom we haue the fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our dayly fode but in the reſt of our ſuſtentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Agayne Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew writeth in the .xv. chapter of his goſpell. That Chriſt toke ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen loues in his handes and ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fyſhes &amp; gaue thankes: But here the Euangelyſte ded not vſe <hi>uaie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barech</hi> (whiche you expounde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways he blyſſed) but <hi>uaiomer todha</hi> which is after the hebrue phraſe)
<pb facs="tcp:18294:10"/>and ſayeng knowledge, (and after the Englyſhe ſpeache) &amp; he gaue thankes: But paraduenture you wyll englyſhe it, that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed than, or ſayd his confiteor. But what ſhould I make ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wordes of the hebrue phraſe of <hi>barech?</hi> for haue not we borowed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame phraſe of the Hebrues and do euen vſe it right well in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpeache whan we ſpeake on this ſorte: Nowe we haue dyned bleſſed be God, or thus: My Lord Protectors grace hath had a faire day on our enemyes (bleſſed be God) and ſende vs ſtyll ſcoch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes. And what do we meane by this (bleſſed be God) but thankes be geuen vnto God for his benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that he vouch ſaued to beſtow theym on vs that ſo vnworthely haue deſerued them at his hand? And therefore we can do no leſſe at the reherſal of ſo many benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:18294:10"/>(ſeyng we acknowledge that that we receyued them al together of him) as it wer in a recompence but ſaye, bleſſed be God, or tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked be God, which is all one effecte, ſauing the one is the phraſe of the Hebrues, and the other the verye englyſhe phraſe. And after this maner is the woorde (bliſſed) take in the .xlvii. chapter of: Geneſis: wheare it is wrytten:</p>
            <p>Ioſeph brought in / Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob his father &amp; ſet him before Pharao: and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Pharao.</p>
            <p>which was as who ſay in engliſh, he thanked Pharao for ſo manye benefites ſhewed vnto his father. Lyke wyſe is it moſt euident that (bleſſe) muſt be taken for geuyng thankes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pſalm. C.iii. whiche begynneth.</p>
            <p>Bleſſe the lorde (O my
<pb facs="tcp:18294:11"/>ſoule) and al that is with in me / bleſſe his holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Bleſſe the Lorde O my ſoule / and forget not all his benefits. whiche forgeueth all thy ſynnes / and healeth al thyne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmites. Whiche ſaueth thy lyfe from deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and crownethe the with mercy &amp; louing kyndnes. whiche ſatiſfieth thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire with good thinges / makynge the yonge and luſty as an Egle. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wo therfore be to al the wreſters of the worde of God. And twyſe wo vnto him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſelye depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the ſame. I praye you why woulde you not call the woordes
<pb facs="tcp:18294:11"/>of conſecration, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of chriſtifi eng? or the wordes of creatyng of Chriſt? or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> make chriſt a new? No, no: ye wer wyſer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo for than dame Hypocriſye coulde neuer ſo ſmothely haue crepte in, nor ſo manye hundreth yeares haue continued. And euen lyke ſleyght ye practyſed whan ye vſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtraunge vocable <hi>Exorcizo te:</hi> for <hi>coniuro te,</hi> I coniure the &amp;c. for we ſhoulde neuer haue ſtrayed ſo far (the coniuryng terme knowen) as to ſay. <hi>A qua benedicta ſit nobis ſalus et uita.</hi> The holy water be oure health and lyfe. Alas alas what ſeas of myſchiefes haue we runne headlyng into by reaſon of youre ſtraunge termes? whiche yf I ſhould proſecute to reherſe one by one I ſhoulde rather be tediouſe vnto the reader than perſwade you to take your penne &amp; to wryte for to redreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Such ſtiffe
<pb facs="tcp:18294:12"/>obſtinacie (the more to be pytyed) is ſo euidetly ſeene in you. I pray God yet of his tender clemencye to ſouple a lytle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pharao hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your flynty harte. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way than with your papiſtical co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecratyng: away with your hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical <hi>Necromancia</hi> &amp; coniuryng? Away with al ſuch couloured ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes: God can not be mocked.<note place="margin">Galat. vt.</note> Therfore it wyl not preuayle you to prattle to hym ſaycnge.</p>
            <p>Lorde Lorde haue not we prophecied in thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: haue not we caſt out deuiles thorow thi name?</p>
            <p>And done many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles thorow thy name?</p>
            <p>For than wyll he anſwere you, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus: For all youre phantaſticall preachynge for all your holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratyng and for all youre colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:18294:12"/>cuniuryng. I neuer knew you departe from me, ye that worke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie. But how long wyll you de voyde of the Lordes feare-how long wyll you defye hys louynge kyndnes? And how long wyll you abuſe his moſt holi word? But yet take hede, take bede, in the meane whyle, leſt an euil ſprite ſaye vnto you</p>
            <p>Ieſus I knowe &amp; Paule I know: but who are ye?</p>
            <p>And with that (for deprauynge of their woordes) haue power to runne on you and wounde you. But to returne to the propoſe. Nowe paraduenture for all this ſpelling of the mater, the papiſtes be ſcant yet wholy reſolued: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt diuine by what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Chriſte woordes at his laſte ſupper, began to be called, <hi>nerba conſecrationis</hi> the workes of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration:
<pb facs="tcp:18294:13"/>And I ſaye they mought wel be called ſo yf thei wer vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, ment, and conſtrued, after the true meanyng of the Hebrue ſpeach, that is: <hi>uerba conſecrationis .i. uerba co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrata hoc eſt uerba ſacra:</hi> the ſacred words: And So ought all the woordes of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be named, as well as they. But now to confirme that the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues vſed ſuche maner of ſpeach neadeth no probacion: But yet, for their ſake that be not much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ucrſant in readynge of the holye ſcripture (which euery wher is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ful of ſuche phr aſes (we wyl adde an example or two: Math. xxiiii.</p>
            <p>Whan ye ſhall ſe the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of deſolation.</p>
            <p>Whiche ſhulde be englyſhed whan ye ſhall ſe the abhominable deſolacion. And after the maner of the ſame language ſpake Paule
<pb facs="tcp:18294:13"/>(thoughe he wrote in an other tongue) to the Romaynes. cap. vii.</p>
            <p>O wretched man that I am (ſayeth he) who ſhall delyuer me from this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of death:</p>
            <p>That is frome thys deadlye or mortall body.</p>
            <p>So Dauid hath in the fyrſt verſe of the .xv. Pſalme.</p>
            <p>Lorde who ſhalbe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into thy pauilyon: or who ſhall dwell in the mountayne of thy holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Wher the Englyſhe tongue woulde requyre it to be tranſlated, in thy holye mountayne.</p>
            <p>But yet in as moche as euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (for whoſe behofe the holye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is indifferently wrytten and
<pb facs="tcp:18294:14"/>prea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched) doth not vnderſtand the ſame Hebrew phraſe: let vs no more chop &amp; change with ſpeches: Let vs no more make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vocables and termes of the hyghe myſteries of our Religion more myſticall &amp; and confuſe than Chriſte hymſel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer made theim. Let vs neyther adde nor take ought awaye frome the worde of God, leſt we ſhalbe ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curſed not of the Pope (whiche is not wont to accurſe for ſuche mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers) but of GOD. Therefore I praye you for the reuerence that ye owe vnto the trueth (I meane) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ieſus Chriſt the verye truethe, that ye wyll no longer vſurpe nor practice the darke termes and (as they be comenly taken) wicked, the termes I ſay of conſecratynge, (or as (you commenly call theym) the wordes of conſecration. I praye you euen for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake to forgo ſuche popyſhe termynge.
<pb facs="tcp:18294:14"/>And call theym whan neade ſhall requyre to talke of theym) whether ſoeuer ye will, the holy woordes, or the woordes of holy ſcripture. And if ye muſt neade yet a whyle name theym by a diffuſe and a ſtraunge terme, call theym the Sacred wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: and I am aſſured ye maye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye wyth Sacred becauſe he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be nere of kinne to maiſter Sacryng your good lorde. The Popes owne derely beloued coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey papiſtes who made and ſette fourth of late the Romyſhe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions (called for the meane ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone) were euen aſhamed to vſurpe any longer the termes of verba con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cecrationis in their booke,<note n="*" place="margin">Called Interim.</note> but the ſame haue they (as it were) abholy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; abrogated namynge theym by a newe terme, but more tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; leſſe odible to chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mens ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res. Yet are not theſe popiſh prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges nothing abaſhed to terme
<pb facs="tcp:18294:15"/>Chriſtes wordes as they wil them ſelfes. Therfore O ye al godli prie ſtes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pretende to be of Chriſts con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do away ſuch fonde ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: Play no more the popiſh prie ſtes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo many external bleſſing &amp; croſſing, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your outwarde waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng &amp; ſhauyng. Ceſſe of your mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelangages before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Play no more (I ſai) Aarons prieſtes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your dedicated te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, with ſeuered chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, with your carnal frequented ſacrifices: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your preſcrpition of veſtures, of time, of meates, of faſting, &amp; faſting dayes,<note place="margin">Hebre. x.</note> for theſe wer but ſhadowes of good thinges to come whiche be alſo come already: the cloudi night is paſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gladſom dai is ſprong,<note place="margin">Iohn. xii.</note> let vs walke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght while we haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght among vs, leſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> darkneſſe come on vs. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> walketh i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, woteth not whether he goeth. And while we haue light, let vs be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue
<pb facs="tcp:18294:15"/>in the lighte, that we maye be chyldren of lyght.</p>
            <p>And this is the condempnation that after the lyght hath come into the worlde men haue yet ſtyll lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued darkenes rather than lyghte. We be paſt chyldehod, away than wyth childiſh phantaſyes. For the houre, commeth and now is,<note place="margin">Iohn. iiii.</note> whan the true worſhippers worſhipp the father in ſpirite, and in truth. For he as a ſprete: and therefore loueth he no carnal thynges, nor outward thynges, but ſpirituall thynges, and inwarde thinges. Therfore al you that be called and choſen to be the miniſters of Chriſte, and the Stewardes of hys ſecrets:<note place="margin">1. Cor. iiii.</note> whan you ſhall miniſtre the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, you may teherſe and alledge Chriſtes holy woordes vnto them after this maner: Good Chriſten brethren this godly Inſtitucion of eatynge the Lordes ſupper: came
<pb facs="tcp:18294:16"/>not vp at the fyrſt of mannes inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, nor was not maintened byma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes pollicie nor continued ſo many yeares (as diuerſe other blynde ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temoniall cuſtomes dyd) withoute playne auctoritie of GODS mooſte holy worde. Therfore dare not I no more than Saynt Paul (for feare of beinge founde an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faytheful ſtewarde, and a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte executour of the Lordes new Teſtament and laſt wyll) alledge and bryng in, for thaſtablyſhment of receyuyng this mooſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſupper, any wordes ymagined of mannes braynes, (appeare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo eloquent, neuer ſo holylyke, or neuer ſo gloriouſe) but euen the veray pure and holy woordes ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Chriſte himſelfe, (the ſame nyghte that he was betrayed) and afterward moſt faythfully wryten by his owne diſciples &amp; our Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes: and nowe at the laſte (by
<pb facs="tcp:18294:16"/>GODS grace) by me pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced worde for woorde as the texte of the Lorde Ieſus Chriſtes newe Teſtament declareth theym: Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore good Chriſtians, lyft vp your hartes to Godwarde, that ye maye heare his holye woordes wyth the eare of faythe: and that you maye take them for the ſtedfaſt ground-werke of your buyldyng, for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall auctoritie, for the trew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, the directe lyne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iuſt ſquiere, the vndeceyuable compaſſe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verye lymites of the true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge and ſincere meanynge of the effectualll ſignification of eatyng the Lordes ſupper.</p>
            <p>But hearken nowe to the holy wordes of the auctoritie, whiche ye ſhall fynde wrytten in the .xxvi. chapter of Matthewe, the .xiiii. of Marke: the .xxii. of Luke, the .vi. of Iohn and in the eleuenth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthi, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18294:17"/>
            <p>And as they dyd eate / Ieſus toke bread: &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had geuen thankes he brake it / &amp; gaue it to the diſciples / &amp; ſayd: Take / eate / thys is my bodye / whiche is geuen for you. This do / in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of me. Lykewiſe alſo wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had ſupped / he toke the cuppe &amp; than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked / ſayeng: drynke ye all of this. For this cup is the new teſtament in my bloude / whiche is ſhedde for many / for the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes. Verely I ſaye vnto you I wil drinke no more of the frute of the
<pb facs="tcp:18294:17"/>vyne tree: vntill that day I drynke it newe in the kyngdome of God. Vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly verely he that putteth his truſt in me / hathe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge life. I am that bread of life / whiche came doune from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: If any man eate of thys bread he ſhal not die / but ſhall haue life for euer.</p>
            <p>And the breade that I wyll geue / is my fleſhe / whiche I wil geue for the lyfe of the world. Verely verely I ſaye vnto you / excepte ye eate the fleſhe of the ſonne of man / and drinke his bloud / ye haue
<pb facs="tcp:18294:18"/>no life in you. whoſoeuer eateth my fleſhe / &amp; dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth my bloud / hath eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall lyfe / and I wil rayſe hym vp at the laſt day. For my fleſhe is meate in dede / and my bloud is drinke in dede: He that eateth my fleſhe / &amp; dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth my bloud / dwelleth in me / &amp; I in him. Doeth this offende you? What &amp; if ye ſe the ſonne of man aſcende vp thether wher he was before? It is the ſprete that quickeneth / the fleſhe profyteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng. The wordes that I ſpeke vnto you / are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite
<pb facs="tcp:18294:18"/>and lyfe. But there are ſome of you / that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not.</p>
            <p>Hetherto haue I reherſed vnto you the veray wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, as for mooſt infallible principles of the chyefe Authore of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans doctrine: as a veray teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of his ineſtimable loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde mankynde: and as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of C<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hriſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion wherby we dare enterpryſe to approche to the Lordes table, and there to eate the Lordes body as it was crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied on the croſſe: and drynke his veray bloud y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was ſhed for oure redemption who wer borne by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the children of wrath and his veray enemyes. This muſt we do for the remembraunce of his moſt beneficial death: and neuer ceaſſe vntyll the Lorde come. For there is not a more odiouſe, nor ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:18294:19"/>a thyng: eyther vnto God or man, as the vice of ingratitude &amp; beaſtely vnkyndnes which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but the forgetfulnes of benefits employed? &amp; the vnthan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kefulnes for good tournes vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruedly ſhewed. And as he that yet ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keteth being not an ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gred hapneth ſome tyme to take ſurfet vntyll the death of his body: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo he that eateth this ſupper not dryuen to with ſpirituall hongre taketh deadely ſurfet of his ſoule And contraryly as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodely meat eaten of our hongry ſtomackes is ſone diſgeſted and noryſheth our bodyes: ſo the fleſhe and bloud of Chriſt eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vs with a ſpirituall hongry deſier noryſheth our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les into euerlaſtyng lyfe. Amen.</p>
            <p>Here haue I treacted ſomwhat largier of the Lordes ſupper than I had entended, for I propoſed nothynge els but to touche a lytle
<pb facs="tcp:18294:19"/>euen ſuperficially of the termes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wer ſo impudently and vnſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly abuſed of the Archepapiſt, which termes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preacher at Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Croſſe (as I heard ſaye) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted to ſpeake of, though he (queſtionles) ful entierly &amp; pyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely handled and confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the reſt of his ſermon. But by like ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the preſcription of the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed tyme beynge ſcarce for to repete in, the whole rablemente of that papiſtical ſermon &amp; the ſame vtterly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fute: either els y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhe and vnlerned rudenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde termes made hym (as he is verely a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo highly learned) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to wynke at theim, &amp; neglect theim, than vnworthely to ſpende any tyme in diſputyng aboute ſo groſſe, ſo playne, and ſo tryflynge a matter. Therfore I praye God ſende vs leſſe acquayntance with ſuche preachers as the fourther
<pb facs="tcp:18294:20"/>was: and more familiaritee with al thoſe that be of that chriſtian crudition and godlye conuerſacion as the later was Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="Scriptural_citations">
            <p>O ye folyſhe Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans / who hathbe witched yon / that ye ſhuld not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the trueth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.5.</note> ye ranne wel / who was a let vnto you / that ye ſhulde not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the trueth: Suche cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell is not of him that called you. A lytel leuen ſowreth the wholelompe of dowe. I haue truſte to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Lorde that ye
<pb facs="tcp:18294:20"/>wylbe none otherwiſe min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. But he that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth you ſhall beare hys iudgement / what ſo euer he be.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer thynges are wrytten afore tyme / they are writen for oure learnyng.<note place="margin">Rome .xv.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beware of falſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / whiche come to you in ſhepes clothing / but in wardli they are rauening wolues. Ye ſhall knowe theym by their fruites.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London in Foſter lane by Iohn Wally.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
